<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of those sad and lamentable accidents, which happened in and about the parish church of Withycombe in the Dartmoores, in Devonshire, on Sunday the 21. of October last, 1638</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121345</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22097</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15319)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22097)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1590:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of those sad and lamentable accidents, which happened in and about the parish church of Withycombe in the Dartmoores, in Devonshire, on Sunday the 21. of October last, 1638</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G[eorge] M[iller] for R: Harford, and are to be sold at his shop in Queenes-head-alley in Pater-noster-row at the guilt Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a final imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Widecombe in the Moor (England : Parish) --  History, (Storm, 1638) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22097:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION OF THOSE SAD AND LAMENTABLE Accidents, which happened in and about the Pariſh Church of <hi>Withycombe</hi> in the <hi>Dartmoores,</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> on Sunday the 21. of <hi>October</hi> laſt, 1638.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 46. 8.</bibl> 
               <p>Come, behold the workes of the Lord, what deſolations hee hath made in the earth.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of George Miller (1601-46) depicting an anchor held by a pair of hands from the clouds</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>R: Harford,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Queenes-head-alley in <hi>Pater-noſter-row</hi> at the guilt Bible, 1638.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22097:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22097:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE RELATION OF thoſe moſt ſtrange and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Accidents, happening in the Pariſh Church of <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thycombe</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> on Sunday the 21. of <hi>October.</hi> 1638.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Chriſtian Readers,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ODS viſible Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and terrible remonſtrances (which every morning are brought to light) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming unto our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſhould bee our obſervation and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22097:3"/>
admonition, <hi>that thereby the inhabitants of the earth may learne Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 5.</note> for to let them paſſe by us (as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter runnes by our doores) unobſerved; argues too much regardleſneſſe of GOD in the way of his Iudgements: <note place="margin">Iſa. 26. 9, 11.</note> not to ſuffer them to ſinke into our affections, and to proove as ſo many terrible warning pieces, which are ſhot off from a watch Tower, to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of an enemies approach, to awaken and affright us; are but a meanes to harden our hearts againſt the Lord, and to awaken his Iuſtice to puniſh us yet more: But <hi>to heare and feare</hi> and to <note place="margin">Paena paucoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terror omnium.</note> doe wickedly no more; to ſearch our hearts and amend our waies is the beſt uſe that can bee made of any of GODS remarkable terrors manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted among us. When GOD is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with us, it ought to be our wiſedome to meete him, and make peace with him: And where wee ſee legible Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of his power and wrath; to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22097:3"/>
learne to ſpell out his meaning tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching our ſelves; to leave off all buſie, malitious, cauſleſſe, and unchriſtianly cenſuring of others, and to turne in upon our ſelves, remembring, <hi>Vel paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendum, vel pereundum, Except wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 13. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>wee ſhall likewiſe periſh.</hi> Certaine it is that wee doe in vaine expect im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity from GODS Iudgements by ſleighting, or contemning them, or increaſing in our ſinnings againſt him. If <hi>Pharoah</hi> by the terrour of thundring and lightning was ſo affrighted that hee ſaith to <hi>Moſes, Intreat the Lord (for it is enough) that there bee no more</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exo 9 28.</note> 
                  <hi>mighty thundrings and Haile.</hi> And if <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula,</hi> out of the feare of thunder, would runne under his bed to hide himſelfe: How much more ſhould we Chriſtians learne to feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the moſt mighty GOD, <hi>whoſe voice only can ſhake the mountaines and rend the rocks, and divide the flames of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>fire;</hi> rends Churches, amazeth, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22097:4"/>
ſtrikes dead at his pleaſure the ſonnes of men? as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee doth whatſoever hee pleaſeth in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, Hee cauſeth the vapours to aſcend from the ends of the earth, and maketh lightnings for the raine, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the winde out of the treaſures of the earth, ſo unſearchable is his Wiſedome, and his waies past finding out.</hi> I ſay, this ſhould awe and humble our hearts before the LORD, riſing up unto more perfection in godlineſſe, doing unto our GOD, more and better ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice then ever hitherto wee have done, reverencing and ſanctifying his dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Name in our hearts: eſpecially when his Iudgements breake in upon men, even in his owne houſe, <hi>mingling their bloud with their ſacrifices,</hi> and that in a moſt terrible manner ſmiting, and wounding, and killing, as in this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Relation may appeare: which for the ſuddenneſſe and ſtrangeneſſe, and in a manner miraculous, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22097:4"/>
the circumſtances thereof, I beleeve few Ages can paralell, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the like. The Lord teach thee to profit thereby, that it may bee as a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached to thee from Heaven by the Lord himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon Sunday the 21. of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> laſt, In the Pariſh Church of <hi>Withycombe</hi> in the <hi>Dartmoores</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> there fell in time of Divine Service a ſtrange darkeneſſe, increaſing more and more, ſo that the people there aſſembled could not ſee to reade in any booke, and ſuddenly in a fearefull and lamentable manner, a mighty thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring was heard, the ratling whereof did anſwer much like unto the ſound and report of many great Cannons, and terrible ſtrange lightening therewith,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22097:5"/>
greatly amazing thoſe that heard and ſaw it, the darkeneſſe increaſing yet more, till they could not (in the interim) ſee one another; the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie lightening came into the Church ſo flaming, that the whole Church was preſently filled with fire and ſmoke, the ſmell whereof was very loathſome, much like unto the ſent of brimſtone, ſome ſaid they ſaw at firſt a great fiery ball come in at the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and paſſe thorough the Church, which ſo affrighted the whole Congregation that the moſt part of them fell downe into their ſeates, and ſome upon their knees, ſome on their faces, and ſome one upon another, with a great cry of burning and ſcalding, they all giving up themſelves for dead, ſuppoſing the laſt Iudgement day was come, and that they had beene in the very flames of Hell.</p>
               <p>The Miniſter of the Pariſh, Maſter <hi>George Lyde,</hi> being in the Pulpit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22097:5"/>
or ſeate where prayers are read, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hee might bee much aſtoniſhed hereat, yet through GODS mercy had no other harme at all in his body, but to his much griefe and amazement heard, and afterward beheld the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table accidents; and although himſelfe was not touched, yet the lightening ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon his poore Wife, fired her ruffe and linnen next to her body, and her cloathes; to the burning of many parts of her body in a very pitifull manner. And one Miſtreſſe <hi>Ditford</hi> ſitting in the pew with the Miniſters wife, was alſo much ſcalded, but the maid and childe ſitting at the pew dore had no harme. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, another woman adventuring to run out of the Church, had her cloathes ſet on fire, and was not only ſtrangely burnt and ſcorched, but had her fleſh torne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her back almoſt to the very bones. Another woeman had her fleſh ſo torne and her body ſo grievouſly burnt, that ſhe died the ſame night.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:22097:6"/>
Alſo one Maſter <hi>Hill</hi> a Gentleman of good account in the Pariſh, ſitting in his ſeate by the Chancell, had his head ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſmitten againſt the wall, through the violence whereof he died that night, no other hurt being found about his body; but his ſonne ſitting in the ſame ſeate had no harme. There was alſo one man more, at the ſame inſtant, of whom it is particularly related, who was Warriner unto Sir <hi>Richard Reynolds,</hi> his head was cloven, his skull rent into three peeces, and his braines throwne upon the ground whole, and the haire of his head, through the violence of the blow at firſt given him, did ſticke faſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pillar or wall of the Church, and in the place a deepe bruiſe into the wall as if it were ſhot againſt with a Cannon bullet.</p>
               <p>Some other perſons were then blaſted and burnt, and ſo grievouſly ſcalded and wounded, that ſince that time they have died therof; and many other not like to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22097:6"/>
recover, notwithſtanding all the meanes that can bee procured to helpe them. Some had their cloaths burnt and their bodies had no hurt, and ſome on the contrary, had their bodies burnt, and their cloathes not touched, and ſome their ſtockings and leggs burnt and ſcalded, and their outward buskings not one thred ſinged. But it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed GOD yet in the midſt of judgement to remember mercy, ſparing ſome and not deſtroying all, yet very many were ſorely ſcalded in divers parts of their bodies, and as all this hurt was done upon the bodies of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſo the hurt alſo that was then done unto the Church was remarkable.</p>
               <p>There were ſome Seates in the Body of the Church turned upſide downe, and yet they which ſate in them had little or no hurt; alſo a Boy ſitting on a ſeate had his hat on, and neare the one halſe thereof was cut off, and he had no hurt, And one man going
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22097:7"/>
out at the Chancell doore, his Dogg running out before him, was whirled about towards the doore and fell downe ſtarke dead: at the ſight whereof his Maſter ſtepped backe within the doore, and GOD preſerved him alive. Alſo the Church it ſelfe was much torne and defaced by the thunder and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and thereby alſo a beame was burſt in the midſt, and fell downe betweene the Miniſter and Clarke and hurt neither; and a weighty great ſtone, neare the Foundation of the Church is torne out and remooved, and the ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple it ſelfe is much rent, and there where the Church was moſt rent, there was leaſt hurt done to the people, and not any one was hurt either with the wood or ſtone, but a maid of <hi>Manaton,</hi> which came thither that afternoone to ſee ſome friends, whom Maſter <hi>Frynd</hi> the <hi>Coroner</hi> by circumſtances, ſuppoſed ſhe was kild with a ſtone, conſidering of her mortall wound, and a great ſtone lying
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22097:7"/>
by her. There were alſo ſtones throwne from the Tower and carried about a great diſtance from the Church, as thick as if a hundred men had beene there throwing, and a number of them of ſuch weight and bigneſſe, that a very ſtrong man could hardly lift them. Alſo one Pinacle of the Tower was torne downe and broke through into the Church.</p>
               <p>Moreover the Pillar againſt which the Pulpit ſtandeth, being but newly whited, is now by this meanes turned black and ſulphry. Furthermore, one man that ſtood in the Chancell, with his face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Bellfrey, obſerved as it were the riſing of duſt or lime, in the lower end of the Church, which ſuddenly (as with a puffe of winde) was whirled up and caſt into his eyes, ſo that hee could not ſee in twelve houres after; but now his ſight is reſtored, and hee hath no other hurt. The terrible lightening being paſt, all the people being in a wonderfull
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22097:8"/>
maze, ſo that they ſpake not one word, by and by one Maſter <hi>Raph Rouſe,</hi> Vinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the Towne, ſtood up, ſaying theſe words, Neighbours, in the name of God ſhall we venture out of the Church, to which M. <hi>Lyde</hi> anſwering, ſaid, it is beſt to make an end of prayers, for it were better to die here then in another place, but they looking about them, and ſeeing the Church ſo terribly rent and torne over their heads, durſt not proceed in their publike devotions, but went forth of the Church.</p>
               <p>And as all this was done within the Church, and unto the Church; ſo there were other accidents without the Church; of which I will give you a touch. There was a Bowling-alley neare unto the Church-yard, which was turned up into pits and heapes, in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner almoſt as if it had beene plowed. At the ſame time alſo at <hi>Brixſton</hi> neare <hi>Plymmouth,</hi> there fell ſuch ſtore of Haile, and ſuch Haile-ſtones, that for quantity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22097:8"/>
they were judged to be as big as ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Turkies eggs; ſome of them were of five, ſome of ſix, and others of ſeven ounces weight.</p>
               <p>We are alſo certainely informed that at the ſame time, as neare as it can bee gueſſed, there fell out the like accident unto the Church at <hi>Norton</hi> in <hi>Somerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> but as yet wee heare of no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hurt therein: Alſo it is related by a Gentleman who travelled in thoſe parts at that time, hee being ſince come to <hi>London,</hi> that where he was the lightening was ſo terrible, fiery and flaming, that they thought their houſes at every flaſh were ſet on fire, in ſomuch that their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſtable were ſo affrighted that they could not rule them.</p>
               <p>All which moſt ſad and lamentable Spectacles were done (as it were) in a moment of time.</p>
               <p>This is the Summe of thoſe diſmall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccidents and terrible examples happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g in the place aforeſaid, as it hath been
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22097:9"/>
carefully extracted out of the letters of Miniſters and other men of quality and good account and credit living not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Pariſh of <hi>Withicombe,</hi> but in the adjoyning Pariſhes and places, and by thoſe that had the full relation from Maſter <hi>Lyde</hi> his own mouth. And the maine drift in the publication of this great ludgement, is for thy humiliation and edification, not onely to acquaint thee with the great and mighty works of Gods Power and luſtice, who in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can do mighty things to us, &amp; arme the creatures againſt us at his owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but alſo to moove pitty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in us towards our Brethren who were patients therein. Which relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you can difficultly reade without ſighs, nor underſtand without teares. I know it is the faſhion of too too many to queſtion and talke, and make things of this nature, but <hi>a nine dayes wonder:</hi> But let us not deceive our ſelves any longer, but conſider, wee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22097:9"/>
have beene lookers on a great while, and others have beene made our exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and felt the ſmart at home and abroad, whilſt wee have gone free; but wee know not how ſoone our turnes and changes may come; theſe accidents might as well have happened to us as them; the LORD therfore in much mercy fit us both for the worſt of times and the beſt of Ends. I end all with that prayer in our Letany, commending thee and this to the bleſſing of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
               <q>From lightening and tempeſt, from Plague, Peſtilence and Famine, from Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell and murder, and from ſuddaine death. Good LORD deliver us.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>THO: WYKES. R. P.</hi> Ep. Lond. Cap. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
